<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Better Ways To Count on Go Figure Math</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/better-ways-to-count/</link><description>Recent content in Better Ways To Count on Go Figure Math</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://gofiguremath.org/better-ways-to-count/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Factorials!</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/better-ways-to-count/factorials/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/better-ways-to-count/factorials/</guid><description>→ Print-friendly version Five-year-old Harry is obsessed with rabbits. For his birthday he got five books about rabbits to put on his shelf: The Care and Keeping of Rabbits, 101 Things You Didn&amp;rsquo;t Know About Rabbits, Common Diseases of Rabbits, How to Draw Rabbits, and Super-Sam and the Giant Were-Rabbit. Harry is now trying to decide how to arrange his new books on his bookshelf. How many ways can he put the books in order?</description></item><item><title>On Choosing</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/better-ways-to-count/on-choosing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/better-ways-to-count/on-choosing/</guid><description>→ Print-friendly version Five-year-old Harry and his family are going on a road trip. &amp;ldquo;Bring something to read on the drive, Harry,&amp;rdquo; his mother tells him. Harry is ecstatic &amp;ndash; that means he gets to bring his rabbit books! He fetches his 12 favorite books about rabbits. His mother is not excited about the prospect of lugging around all those books for the whole trip. &amp;ldquo;Not all of them, Harry,&amp;rdquo; she tells him.</description></item><item><title>Path Counting</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/better-ways-to-count/path-counting/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/better-ways-to-count/path-counting/</guid><description>→ Print-friendly version In the city of Trafficville there is a region where all the streets are one-way. If a car drives into this region, it can only drive south or east. (It&amp;rsquo;s really not very practical. The city council is debating what should be done about it.)
Restaurant owner Rosa Gustaroni, who is going to work this morning, wants to drive from the bakery (at the green star) to her restaurant (at the orange star).</description></item></channel></rss>