<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Go Figure Math</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Go Figure Math</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gofiguremath.org/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Counterfeit Detective</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/counterfeit-detective/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/counterfeit-detective/</guid><description>It was a dark and stormy night. Private detective Harriet Hesterton had been recruited by her colleague Mahmud Mufti to assist in a case. Some shadowy organization was making counterfeit coins and distributing them to conspiring (or coerced) store owners, who mixed them in with real coins to hide their tracks before giving them as change to customers. Harriet and Mahmud were at what they suspected was one such store.</description></item><item><title>The Magic Checkerboard</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/the-magic-checkerboard/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/the-magic-checkerboard/</guid><description>Two siblings, Janelle and Terrence, are visiting their friends Amy and Sarah. Terrence has just won a game of checkers against Amy for the second time in a row.
&amp;ldquo;Hey Sarah,&amp;rdquo; Amy said. &amp;ldquo;This checkerboard reminds me of the magic trick you showed me yesterday.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Magic trick?&amp;rdquo; asked Janelle.
&amp;ldquo;The one where you cut up the grid,&amp;rdquo; Amy prompted her big sister. &amp;ldquo;Let&amp;rsquo;s show Terrence and Janelle!&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Okay,&amp;rdquo; said Sarah, grinning.</description></item><item><title>An Interplanetary Currency</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/an-interplanetary-currency/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/an-interplanetary-currency/</guid><description>In the year 3187, space traveler Alex Ng stops to withdraw some money from her bank account in the standard interplanetary currency. Since extraterrestrials don&amp;rsquo;t have five fingers, doing business in multiples of one, five, and ten Earth dollars doesn&amp;rsquo;t really make sense, and neither does doing business in multiples of one, 17, and 68 Yrxiggian knuggyts. Instead, the interplanetary currency is called a blyp, and it comes in multiples of 1, 2, 4, 8, and so on: the powers of 2.</description></item><item><title>Pirate Gold</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/pirate-gold/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/pirate-gold/</guid><description>The five crew members of a small pirate ship have just completed a raid in another crew&amp;rsquo;s territory, and they now have 100 gold coins to split among themselves.
&amp;ldquo;What a raid!&amp;rdquo; says the captain Anastasia. &amp;ldquo;Look at the feather in my hat &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s been torn to shreds.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Aye,&amp;rdquo; agrees the first mate Bartholomew. &amp;ldquo;I have a new hole in my coat.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Lucky my compass didn&amp;rsquo;t get smashed while we were retreating back to sea,&amp;rdquo; remarks the navigator Cornelius.</description></item><item><title>Stargazing</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/stargazing/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/stargazing/</guid><description>Paula is re-doing her entryway, and she has decided to inlay a big star-shaped tile into the ceiling. She found a tilework company, Mort&amp;rsquo;s Tilework, that can cut tile into complex shapes like the one she has in mind:
Mort&amp;rsquo;s Tilework has a seemingly simple pricing scheme for a tile order: $0.25 per square centimeter of area plus $0.10 per centimeter of perimeter. To place her order, Paula needs to send in both a schematic of her shape and her calculations for the area and perimeter of the shape.</description></item><item><title>A Magic Trick</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/a-magic-trick/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/a-magic-trick/</guid><description>Private detective Harriet Hesterton picked up the phone.
&amp;ldquo;Hi Detective Hesterton. This is Gus Spurious,&amp;rdquo; said the voice on the other side.
&amp;ldquo;Good afternoon. Do you have another suspicious proof to examine?&amp;rdquo; she replied, remembering their last conversation.
&amp;ldquo;No,&amp;rdquo; said Gus. &amp;ldquo;I have a magic trick I can&amp;rsquo;t figure out. My friend Alina showed it to me and ever since then I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to understand how it works.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Okay,&amp;rdquo; Harriet told him, picking up a pen.</description></item><item><title>Moving Day</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/moving-day/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/moving-day/</guid><description>Leslie Armstrong runs a sporting goods store. Business has been good and the store needs to move to a larger space to accommodate all its customers. Leslie has hire five moving trucks &amp;ndash; we can call them Trucks 1 through 5 &amp;ndash; to transport all the supplies, and she is now deciding what trucks will carry what supplies.
She has 9 identical basketballs in stock on moving day, as well as 61 volleyballs, 88 baseballs, and 323 golf balls.</description></item><item><title>Bridging the Gap</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/bridging-the-gap/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/bridging-the-gap/</guid><description>The town of Isleton, renowned for its widespread decorative woodwork and fine cheeses, spans a cluster of four islands:
a. Morton is a tour guide for the town, based on the east side of the south island (in the blue building). He advertises to tourists that his walking tour crosses every bridge in the city. To minimize the amount of walking on the tour, Morton decides he&amp;rsquo;d like to plan the tour&amp;rsquo;s path so it crosses each bridge exactly once, ideally starting and ending at the same location.</description></item><item><title>A Recurrence Riddle</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/a-recurrence-riddle/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/a-recurrence-riddle/</guid><description>Two sisters, Amy and Sarah, are staying busy on a long car ride. Sarah is reading a book. Amy is poking her older sister and trying to start a conversation.
To give Amy something to do, Sarah looks up from her book and says, &amp;ldquo;Look &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;ll give you a math puzzle, and once you get the answer, I&amp;rsquo;ll put down the book and talk with you.&amp;rdquo; Amy is up for the challenge and agrees.</description></item><item><title>A Triangle of Prime Opportunity</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/a-triangle-of-prime-opportunity/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/a-triangle-of-prime-opportunity/</guid><description>Suppose we have a triangle, and suppose we also draw its altitudes (that is, the heights if we treat each side length as the base):
If the three side lengths and the three altitudes are all integers AND they&amp;rsquo;re all different from each other, is it ever possible for four of the six numbers to be prime?
Nicki and Dave disagree what the answer should be: Dave thinks it should be possible, while Nicki thinks it&amp;rsquo;s probably impossible.</description></item><item><title>Spider Socks</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/spider-socks/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/spider-socks/</guid><description>Harvey the Spider is putting on his argyle socks and boots in the morning. Naturally, he has 8 socks and 8 boots to put on, and for every one of his 8 legs, he has to put the sock on before the boot.
Let&amp;rsquo;s number Harvey&amp;rsquo;s feet 1 through 8, call the argyle sock for his $i\textrm{th}$ foot $A_i$, and call the boot for his $i\textrm{th}$ foot $B_i$. Then one valid order Harvey could use for putting on socks and boots is</description></item><item><title>Duo Dominoes</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/duo-dominoes/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/duo-dominoes/</guid><description>Paula would like to re-tile the hallway with those nice domino-shaped tiles she discovered while redoing the kitchen. The tiles are 1x2, and the hallway is just wide enough for one of these tiles to fit horizontally.
Paula knows she doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to tile the hallway all the way to the back of the house, since the carpet from the den can stretch across some portion of the hallway; she hasn&amp;rsquo;t decided exactly how long the tiling will be, though.</description></item><item><title>Pennies</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/pennies/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/pennies/</guid><description>Suppose you have 8 pennies, and you arrange 7 of them in a cluster like this:Now suppose you take the eighth penny and place it at the top:
And then you roll it around the outside of the cluster, never letting it slide and always staying in contact with the cluster:
Viewing the whole scenario from above, how many 360-degree rotations does the outer penny make during one trip around the central cluster?</description></item><item><title>Swans</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/swans/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/swans/</guid><description>A flock of $n$ swans is sitting peacefully on a pond. Then, suddenly, one of the swans hears something in a bush at the water&amp;rsquo;s edge, and it takes off and flies away.
Suppose that if $k$ swans have flown away, the probability of another swan subsequently joining them is $1-\frac{1}{k+3}$ (so the more swans fly, the more likely it is that more swans fly also). What is the probability that the entire flock of $n$ swans flies away once the first one takes off?</description></item><item><title>City Council</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/city-council/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/city-council/</guid><description>A certain city is entirely inhabited by knights and liars. Knights, consistently chivalrous, always tell the truth. Liars, on the contrary, never tell the truth. One can never tell whether a citizen is a knight or a liar just by their appearance.
The city council, recently elected, is composed of twelve of the city&amp;rsquo;s most eminent inhabitants. One day they come together to a council meeting. They all recognize each other and know which members of the group are knights and which are liars.</description></item><item><title>Cut Corners</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/cut-corners/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/cut-corners/</guid><description>Paula is re-doing the floor tiling in the kitchen. The space is shaped like an 8x8 square, except that one corner is missing to make room for the refrigerator and the opposite corner is missing to leave space for the dishwasher.
Paula found a domino-shaped (1x2) tile she&amp;rsquo;d like to use to tile the space:
How many ways are there for her to tile the kitchen with this shape?
The solution can be found here.</description></item><item><title>Troll Trouble</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/troll-trouble/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/troll-trouble/</guid><description>You have been captured by an evil troll. The troll doesn&amp;rsquo;t have much to do besides capture people, so to amuse itself it&amp;rsquo;s made a bargain with you: you are to play a certain game with the troll, and if you win, you go free.
The game starts with a pile of 50 pebbles. Players take turns removing either 1 or 2 pebbles from the pile. The player to take away the last pebble from the pile loses the game.</description></item><item><title>Leapfrog</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/leapfrog/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/leapfrog/</guid><description>Three frogs are sitting on the coordinate plane: one at (0, 0), one at (1, 0), and one at (0, 1). They play a game of leapfrog such that whenever one frog hops over another, the leapee is at the midpoint of where the leaper leaped from and where the leaper landed. For example, here are two valid leaps in the game: (0, 0) to (2, 0) and then (0, 1) to (4, -1).</description></item><item><title>A Phony Proof</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/a-phony-proof/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/a-phony-proof/</guid><description>Private detective mathematician Harriet Hesterton was sitting calmly at her desk one day absently flipping through case files when her phone rang.
&amp;ldquo;My name is Gus Spurious,&amp;rdquo; said the voice on the other end, &amp;ldquo;and I have a problem. See, I was playing with a bit of algebra the other day, and I proved something that just looks completely wrong. I might&amp;rsquo;ve just made a breakthrough that changes the face of mathematics, but I can&amp;rsquo;t figure out how my result could be true!</description></item><item><title>Salt and Pepper</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/salt-and-pepper/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/salt-and-pepper/</guid><description>Chef Charles is creating a couple of salt-and-pepper blends to simplify the process of seasoning a dish. He starts with two ordinary salt and pepper shakers, both the same size and both filled the same amount. To make the seasoning blends, Charles measures out one teaspoon of pepper from the pepper shaker and adds it to the salt shaker, stirring to mix in the pepper evenly; he then measures out one teaspoon of this salt-and-pepper mix, adds it back to the pepper shaker, and stirs.</description></item><item><title>Light Bulbs</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/light-bulbs/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/light-bulbs/</guid><description>Rachel&amp;rsquo;s math club meets in a classroom at the end of a long hallway in her school. This long hallway is lit by a row of 100 light bulbs, each with a chain attached to it that toggles the light bulb on or off when pulled.
One day, Rachel arrives much earlier than everyone else, and she sees that the hallway is still dim: no one has turned on the hallway bulbs yet.</description></item><item><title>Wolf, Goat, Lettuce</title><link>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/wolf-goat-lettuce/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gofiguremath.org/posts/wolf-goat-lettuce/</guid><description>Here&amp;rsquo;s a classic puzzle:
Farmer Brown is taking his goods to market: a goat, a wolf, and a head of lettuce. There is a river on the way to the market. Ordinarily there would be a bridge spanning the river. But today the bridge has collapsed, and the only way of getting across is a small rowboat, just big enough for Farmer Brown and one of his items.
This poses a problem.</description></item></channel></rss>